Guide to the Geoffrey T. Hellman Papers MSS.050
Fales Library and Special Collections
Geoffrey T. Hellman Papers
1842-1971
Fales Library and Special Collections
Hellman, Geoffrey, 1907-
MSS.050
26 Linear Feet (51 boxes)
Geoffrey T. Hellman was a long-time contributor to The New Yorker ("Talk of the Town" section in particular) and other periodicals, and wrote extensively about institutions such as: the American Museum of Natural History, the Smithsonian, and the Metropolitan Museum of Art. The collection gives a glimpse into the operation of The New Yorker from the 1930's through 1960's. Research for Hellman's articles, his correspondence, and manuscripts are contained in this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Geoffrey T. Hellman were donated by Hellman to the Fales Library of New York University on June 15, 1969. A second donation of material was made by his daughter, Katharine, in November of 1985. Other collections of his papers are located in the New York Public Library and in the New York Historical Society. Geoffrey Hellman, a staff writer for The New Yorker, felt that the papers that had not yet been donated should stay in New York rather than go to his alma mater, Yale University, because the materials deal mostly with the city; hence, the donation to New York University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical Note
Geoffrey T. Hellman was born in New York City in 1907, and was the son of writer, George Hellman. He attended Yale and contributed to the Yale News, Yale Record and the Yale Literary Magazine. Upon graduating in 1928, he wrote for the New York Herald Tribune's Sunday book supplement thanks to a recommendation by Thorton Wilder. By 1929, he secured a position at The New Yorker magazine as a reporter for the "Talk of the Town" section. Though he contributed to numerous publications in his career, he would be affiliated and most firmly identified with The New Yorker.
While with The New Yorker, Hellman wrote extensively about New York institutions such as the New York Zoological Society and the Bronx Zoo, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Metropolitan Opera House, the Museum of Modern Art, the New York Public Library, the Pierpont Morgan Library, the United Nations, and the New York Stock Exchange, to promote public awareness of these institutions and of interesting events they sponsored. He also wrote about prominent people such as author Louis Auchincloss; New York Parks Commissioner Robert Moses, who sent him story ideas; and architect Frank Lloyd Wright. Because of his background and family connections, he was also The New Yorker's link to New York society and he reported on parties, local clubs and societies such as the Grolier Club, the Explorer's Club, the National Audubon Society, and the American Geographical Society, and exclusive restaurants, from which he collected an impressive number of menus.
His books include compilations of his pieces that appeared in The New Yorker ('How to Disappear for an Hour' and 'Mrs. De Peyster's Parties') and a book about the Smithsonian Institution ('Octopus on the Mall') and a history of the American Museum of Natural History ('Bankers, Bones and Beetles').
From 1936-1938, he was also the associate editor of Life Magazine. During World War II, Hellman was in Washington D.C. where he wrote for the Office of Inter-American affairs, the War Department and helped to write a top-secret history of the OSS.
In addition to his pursuits as a writer, Hellman was also an enthusiastic butterfly collector. Hellman died in 1977.
Sources:
Hellman, Geoffrey T. "All about Geoffrey Hellman." Saturday Review of Literature, v. XXX; no. 39; 1947.
The Geoffrey T. Hellman Papers; MSS 50; Fales Library and Special Collections, New York University Libraries.
Scope and Content Note
The Hellman Papers measured approximately 28 linear feet prior to processing. The collection was reduced to 26 linear feet after the removal of duplicate material. The Hellman Papers contain correspondence, research materials, drafts, proofs, manuscripts, and final publication material from his very prolific, nearly fifty year writing career.
Because Hellman intended this collection to be a record of his career and of the history of The New Yorker, he included in the donation notes intended for whoever would be using the collection with his insights about writing for The New Yorker. These notes are referred to in the finding aid as "notes to the user".
The collection has been divided into 16 series. The collection is organized primarily by type of article, which is determined by the magazine's own classification. The order of the series was determined by the number of articles Hellman wrote in a specific category. Series one consists of "Talk of the Town" articles, which comprised the bulk of Hellman's published work for The New Yorker. Series two consists of "Profiles." Series three is entitled "Subject Category" and it consists of articles organized by subject rather than type of article. Series four consists of "Casuals." Series five consists of "Onward and Upward" pieces. Series six consists of "Reporter At Large" pieces. Series seven contains information about Hellman's activities during World War II. Series eight consists of all the other kinds of articles Hellman wrote for The New Yorker. Series nine consists of information about The New Yorker style. Series 10 consists of articles Hellman wrote for publications other than The New Yorker. Series 11 consists of information about Hellman's published books. Series 12 consists of articles that cannot be identified by article type or publication that appear not to have been published. Series 13 consists of correspondence. Series 14 consists of Hellman's speeches. Series 15 consists of personal material unrelated to his career. Series 16 consists of financial information.
Oversized material that did not fit in the oversized boxes is housed in the map case under the collection name. Galleys are filed in a drawer set in the workroom.
Series Description
Series 1. Talk of the Town
Series 1 consists of short pieces entitled "Talk of the Town" and even shorter pieces within the "Talk of the Town" department entitled "Notes and Comments" and "Anecdotes." The subjects for "Talk of the Town" and "Notes and Comments" pieces were New York City events, places, and personalities. The "Anecdotes" were brief accounts written from anecdotes sent in by The New Yorker readers or amusing newspaper or magazine errors. The "Talk of the Town" articles are arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically within each subject. The "Notes and Comments" articles are arranged chronologically.
Included in this series are photocopies of the published articles, newspaper clippings, tearsheets, photographs, drafts, telegrams, postcards, leaflets, pamphlets, booklets, notes from Hellman to the user, drafts, edited drafts, financial records, galleys, edited galleys, revised galleys, and editorial proofs.
Series 2. Profiles
Series 2 consists of articles entitled "Profiles," published between 1931 and 1968, in which Hellman wrote biographical sketches of prominent and interesting individuals. Unlike "A Reporter At Large" articles in which Hellman reported on an interview with a subject without critically evaluating what was said, the "Profiles" were intended to be an objective portrayal of the subject, arrived at through interviews with the subject, his associates, and anyone familiar with him. The articles are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the subject with research material and correspondence arranged chronologically within each folder.
In folder 6, are three pen and ink drawings of artist George Biddle, two by himself and a third by his wife, artist Helene Sardeau. Folder 30 contains an addendum to the collection by the Fales Special Collections staff consisting of an invitation to an exhibition on Albert Gallatin. In folder 45, is a sketch by architect Le Corbusier of his design for the U.N. building.
Series 3. Subject Category
Series 3 consists of broad subjects, such as influential people and institutions, about which Hellman wrote several different kinds of articles between 1938 and 1968. It is arranged alphabetically by subject, and within each subject, the material is arranged chronologically.
This series includes photographs, correspondence to and from Hellman, maps, newspaper clippings, research books, memos, notes to the user, notes, drafts, edited drafts, galleys, edited galleys, editorial proofs, tearsheets, photocopies of articles, reprints of articles, legal documents and financial records. Oversize material has been filed in separate oversize boxes, the map case, and a separate "Galley" file. This series contains extensive correspondence between artist Alexander Calder and Hellman, including sketches by Calder (folder 46). In the material on Frank Crowninshield, editor of Vanity Fair magazine, are two letters from author William Dean Howells, dated August 4, 1889 and February 28, 1896 (folder 54) and a copy of the play, "Vanity Fair", Hellman wrote about Crowninshield that was never produced (folder 55). Under the subject heading "Jewish Dynastic Families" are letters from artist Max Ernst, an imitation The New Yorker magazine published for Adolph Lewisohn's birthday, and genealogical blueprints and charts.
Series 4. Casuals
Series 4 consists of humorous articles of one to four printed pages called "Casuals" by Hellman and The New Yorker staff. The published articles date from 1936 to 1963. The series is arranged alphabetically by the title of the article.
This series includes correspondence to and from Hellman, memos, tear sheets, photocopies of articles, edited drafts, rough copies of the magazine, reviews, galleys, revised galleys, editorial proofs, newspaper clippings, and financial records. The galleys and editorial proofs, because of their size, have been stored in a box for oversized material and are shelved separately. The largest collection of "Casuals" outside this series is in the subject category series, "Jewish Dynastic Families."
Series 5. Onward and Upward
Series 5 consists of articles entitled "Onward and Upward." The articles are about museums, art collections, or people associated with the arts or sciences, usually about ten printed pages in length. The following categories of arts and sciences are arranged alphabetically "Onward And Upward With The Arts," "Onward And Upward With The Arts And Sciences," "Onward And Upward With The Sciences," and "Onward And Upward With The Social Sciences." The articles are also arranged alphabetically by title within each of these categories. The research material and correspondence associated with the articles are arranged chronologically within each folder. The articles were published between 1941 and 1966.
Included in this series are photocopies of articles, correspondence to and from Hellman, tearsheets of articles, telegrams, postcards, leaflets, pamphlets, notes from Hellman to the user, drafts, financial records, a rough draft of the magazine, legal documents, newspaper clippings, galleys, revised galleys, and editorial proofs.
Series 6. A Reporter at Large
Series 6 consists of articles between four and ten printed pages entitled "A Reporter At Large," published between 1933 and 1960, in which Hellman as the reporter writes about something seen, or someone interviewed. The articles are arranged alphabetically by subject, and research material and correspondence are arranged chronologically.
The series also contains photocopies of articles, notes to the user from Hellman, pamphlets, story suggestions, drafts, "Talk of the Town" tearsheets, "Talk of the Town" galleys, "Talk of the Town" editorial proofs, galleys, editorial proofs, newspaper clippings, tearsheets, research material, edited drafts, "Talk of the Town" drafts, photocopies of galleys that Hellman had cut and glued on yellow paper, and financial records.
Series 7. World War II
Series 7 consists of records of Hellman's service during World War II and articles written during or about that period. The first three folders are arranged chronologically and consist of documents and correspondence to and from Hellman. The next three folders are arranged chronologically and consist of articles that were published for The New Yorker. The articles within the folders are arranged alphabetically, and research material and correspondence are arranged chronologically.
Series 8. Other Articles In The New Yorker
Series 8 consists of articles published in The New Yorker which were not numerous enough to constitute a separate series. This series is composed of pieces entitled "The Department of Amplification" and "That Was New York." The articles are arranged alphabetically by title with the finished article in front and research material and correspondence arranged chronologically following. Included in this series are memos from Hellman, story suggestions, correspondence, press releases, notes, drafts, edited drafts, tearsheets, galleys, edited galleys, editorial proofs, blueprints, photos, and financial records. Oversized galleys and editorial proofs are housed in oversize flat boxes and the map case.
Series 9. The New Yorker Style
This series consists of material that relates to The New Yorker's style and administration arranged alphabetically, and chronologically within each folder. Included in this series are magazine, booklets, newsletters, bulletins, and lists. The reprints of articles by other The New Yorker staff writers were included in the material when it was accessioned, indicating that these are articles that Hellman admired. "Hiroshima" by John Hersey is one of the most important and well-known New Yorker articles.
Series 10. Other Publications
Series 10 consists of articles written between 1938 and 1971 for publications other than The New Yorker. The files within this series are arranged alphabetically by title of publication, and chronologically within each folder. Miscellaneous copies of magazines to which Hellman contributed have been included at the end of this series and are listed in the container list. The Life Magazine "Close-ups" (folders 14 through 23) are arranged alphabetically by subject, and chronologically within each folder. This series consists of personal notes from Hellman to any subsequent user of the material, correspondence to and from Hellman, newspaper clippings, drafts, edited drafts, galleys, edited galleys, editorial proofs, photocopies of paste-ups of finished articles, tearsheets, magazines, and financial records.
Series 11. Books
Series 11 consists of two books, How To Disappear For An Hour(1947) and Mrs. DePeyster's Parties (1963), which were primarily composed of "Casuals" and "Profiles" that had been previously published in The New Yorker. Printed copies of the books are described in this finding aid under Separated Material. Copies of two bound clippings volumes originally separated from the series have been included. There are four books by Hellman in this collection; the other two, Bankers, Bones, and Beetles and The Octopus On The Mall, are filed in the subject category (Series 3). The material in this series consists of correspondence to and from Hellman, business contracts, tearsheets from The New Yorker, edited galleys, typeset galleys, book jackets and a book binding, book reviews, press clippings, promotional ads and blurbs, a copyright assignment list, and royalty reports. The material is arranged chronologically.
Series 12. Unpublished Articles
Series 12 consists of three articles written between 1941 and 1964 which are not identified as having been written for a specific publication and which do not appear to have been published. They are arranged alphabeticaly by subject, with research material and correspondence for each article arranged chronologically. This series consists of correspondence to and from Hellman, notes, drafts, edited drafts, tearsheets from "Talk of the Town," and booklets.
Series 13. Correspondence
Series 13 consists of correspondence to and from Hellman, and correspondence not addressed to him that he saved because it referred to his work or was important to the history of The New Yorker. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically. The series also contains solicitations for articles from magazines other than The New Yorker which Hellman declined; drafts of articles turned down by The New Yorker; and correspondence between Hellman and magazines other than The New Yorker, usually about articles that were later not published.
Series 14. Speeches
Series 14 consists of Hellman's speeches. This series includes edited drafts, correspondence to and from Hellman, leaflets, booklets, and financial records. Most of the speeches are autobiographical about Hellman's experiences at The New Yorker and they contain much of the same information as his article for Author's Guild Bulletin (Series 1, folder 34).
Series 15. Personal
This series consists of material that is unrelated to Hellman's career as a journalist. The material includes mimeographed notices and newsletters, edited drafts of speeches, leaflets, booklets, photocopied material, and correspondence to and from Hellman. The series primarily contains information about some of Hellman's club activities because he was secretive about his private life. The few personal letters he donated are filed in the correspondence series.
Series 16. Finances
Series 16 consists of financial records documenting payments to Hellman for story ideas and articles published in The New Yorker. Financial records of The New Yorker payments to Hellman are also filed throughout the collection.
Arrangement
Folders are primarily arranged alphabetically by subject/author.
The files are grouped into 16 series.
Missing Title
Series I: Talk of the Town
Series II: Profiles
Series III: Subject Category
Series IV: Casuals
Series V: Onward and Upward
Series VI: A Reporter at Large
Series VII: World War II
Series VIII: Other Articles in The New Yorker
Series IX: The New Yorker Style
Series X: Other Publications
Series XI: Books
Series XII: Unpublished Articles
Series XIII: Correspondence
Series XIV: Speeches
Series XV: Personal
Series XVI: Finances
Oversize - Series I: Talk of the Town
Oversize - Series II: Profiles
Oversize - Series III: Subject Category
Oversize - Series IV: Casuals
Oversize - Series V: Onward and Upward
Oversize - Series VI: A Reporter at Large
Oversize - Series VII: World War II
Oversize - Series VIII: Other Articles in The New Yorker
Oversize - Series X: xsOther Publications
Oversize - Series XI: Books
Oversize - Series XIII: Correspondence
Separated Material
Seven printed titles (8 items total) have been separated from the collection:
Hellman, Geoffrey. How To Disappear For An Hour. New York: Dodd, Mead and Company. 1947.
Hellman, Geoffrey. Kommt ein Vogel geflogen. Switzerland: Verlag AG Zurich. 1960.
Hellman, Geoffrey. Mrs. DePeyster's Parties And Other Lively Studies From The New Yorker. New York: The Macmillan Company. 1963.
Hellman, Geoffrey. The Smithsonian: The Octopus on the Mall. New York: J. B. Lippincott Company. 1966.
Hellman, Geoffrey. Bankers, Bones and Beetles. New York: The Natural History Press. 1968.
Hellman, George. Lanes of Memory. New York: Alfred A. Knopf. 1927. (2 copies)
Hellman, George. Peacock's Feather. Indianapolis: The Bobbs Merrill Company. 1931.
Art museums -- New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.).; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Art museums -- Exhibitions.; Journalism -- United States.; Gossip columnists.; American fiction -- 20th century.; New York (N.Y.) |x Museums.; Clippings (information artifacts); Journalism, Scientific.; Periodical editors |z New York (State) |z New York.; Reviews (document genre); Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Art museums |x Public relations.; New Yorker (New York, N.Y.: 1925); Manuscripts for publication.; Articles.; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.); Photographs.; Authors and publishers -- United States.; Tear sheets.; Drawings; New York (N.Y.) |v Newspapers |v Periodicals |v Journalism.; New York Botanical Garden; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Le Corbusier, 1887-1965; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984; Schiff, Dorothy, 1903-1989; Ross, Harold Wallace, 1892-1951; Ripley, Sidney Dillon, 1913-2001; Plimpton, Francis T. P. (Francis Taylor Pearsons), 1900-1983; Crane, Joe, 1902-; Cerf, Bennett, 1898-1971; Calder, Alexander, 1898-1976; American Museum of Natural History; D'Harnoncourt, Rene, 1901-1968; Dale, Chester, b. 1883; Achelis, Elisabeth, 1880-1973; Smithsonian Institution; Sulzberger, Arthur Hays, 1891-1968; White, E. B. (Elwyn Brooks), 1899-1985; White, Katharine Sergeant Angell
- Series 1: Talk of the Town
  - A, 1933-1967; 31142040613815 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Geographical Society, 1960-1969; 31142040613815 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Antiques Shows, 1954-1965; 31142040613815 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Auchincloss, Louis, 1938-1969; 31142040613815 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - B, 1940-1970; 31142040613815 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Borough Librarians, 1953; 31142040613815 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - British Information Services, 1950-1966; 31142040613815 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bronx Zoo, 1947-1968; 31142040613815 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - C, 1945-1969; 31142040613815 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carnegie Institution in Washington, 1958-1968; 31142040613815 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Consul Generals, 1950-1966; 31142040613815 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - D, 1946-1968; 31142040613815 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - E, 1945-1969; 31142040613823 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Explorers Club, 1964-1969; 31142040613823 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - F, 1939-1969; 31142040613823 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - G, 1929-1969; 31142040613823 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Grolier Club, 1958-1964; 31142040613823 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - H, 1946-1969; 31142040613823 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - I, J, 1948-1969; 31142040613823 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - K, 1948-1963; 31142040613823 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - L, 1932-1969; 31142040613823 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - M, 1930-1967; 31142040613831 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Menus, 1949-1963; 31142040613831 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1949-1969; 31142040613831 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Metropolitan Opera House, 1952-1961; 31142040613831 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Moses, Robert, 1940-1954; 31142040613831 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1946-1968; 31142040613831 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - N, 1946-1973; 31142040613831 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - National Audubon Society, 1950-1962; 31142040613831 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - New York Public Library, 1941-1969; 31142040613831 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - New York Zoological Society, 1950-1969; 31142040613831 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Nonagenarians, 1948-1968; 31142040613831 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - O, 1946-1962; 31142040613849 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Octogenarians, 1948-1963; 31142040613849 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Our Own Baedeker, 1946-1949; 31142040613849 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - P, 1948-1968; 31142040613849 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Parties, 1955-1963; 31142040613849 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Pierpont Morgan Library, 1948-1963; 31142040613849 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Q, 1968; 31142040613849 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - R, 1942-1968; 31142040613849 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Ritz-Carlton Hotel, 1950-1951; 31142040613849 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - S, 1932-1968; 31142040613849 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Shakespearean Societies and Debates, 1947-1963; 31142040613856 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Stock Exchange, 1947-1961; 31142040613856 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Style, 1952-1969; 31142040613856 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - T, 1940-1964; 31142040613856 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - U,V, 1933-1969; 31142040613856 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - United Nations, 1946-1963; 31142040613856 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - W, 1940-1969; 31142040613856 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1952-1961; 31142040613856 (Box 5, Folder 50)